<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning-peece for England being a discovery of a Jesuiticall design to dismember Wales from England, to the ruine of both : together with undeniable reasons and arguments, proving the indispensable necessity of appeals from Wales to the courts at Westminister ... : humbly tendred to the consideration of His Highness the Lord Protector and his council / by a well-wisher to the peace and tranquility of this nation, P.P.</title>
            <author>P. P., Well-wisher to the peace and tranquility of this nation.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P94</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13024144</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13024144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56774)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 394:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning-peece for England being a discovery of a Jesuiticall design to dismember Wales from England, to the ruine of both : together with undeniable reasons and arguments, proving the indispensable necessity of appeals from Wales to the courts at Westminister ... : humbly tendred to the consideration of His Highness the Lord Protector and his council / by a well-wisher to the peace and tranquility of this nation, P.P.</title>
                  <author>P. P., Well-wisher to the peace and tranquility of this nation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for N. Ekins, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING-PEECE FOR ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Being a Diſcovery of a JESUITICALL Deſign, to Diſmember <hi>WALES</hi> from <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> to the ruine of both.</p>
            <p>Together with undeniable <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> proving the indiſpenſable neceſsity of Appeals from <hi>Wales</hi> to the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Certiorar. Writs</hi> of <hi>Error, Habeas Corpus, Quo minus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Subpaena's</hi> out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and <hi>Subpaena's</hi> out of the High-Court of CHANCERY.</p>
            <p>Eſtabliſhed by ſeverall Acts of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly tendred to the Conſideration of his <hi>Highneſs</hi> the LORD PROTECTOR and his <hi>Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Well-wiſher to the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquility</hi> of this NATION. <hi>P.P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. Ekins,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96664:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96664:2"/>
            <p>IT hath been, and of late, a much uſed Maxime, <hi>Divide &amp; impera;</hi> In order therunto perſons <hi>ill-affected</hi> to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace,</hi> by reflecting too much upon their own <hi>advantages,</hi> do imploy their endeavour to ſever <hi>Appeals</hi> from the Cognizance or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions of the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be within themſelves abſolute <hi>Maſters</hi> of their own <hi>deſires,</hi> with little heed looking back upon the <hi>common Enemy,</hi> that by theſe Wiles inſenſibly inſnare them, under pretence of <hi>advancing themſelves,</hi> to ruine the whole <hi>Government:</hi> For the Wiſdom of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors purchaſed our <hi>Union</hi> with much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of <hi>Blood, Money,</hi> and <hi>Time,</hi> to prevent thoſe great Inconveniencies that the inconſiderateneſs of ſome, probably of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:96664:3"/>excuſable, will inevitably draw upon us by an intention they have to petition the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power,</hi> to bar the Inhabitants of <hi>Wales</hi> of the benefit of thoſe Writs of <hi>Appeal, Certiorar. Writs</hi> of <hi>Error, Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Quo minus,</hi> and <hi>Subpaenas</hi> out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and <hi>Subpaenas</hi> out of the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Chancery</hi> establiſhed by ſo many Acts of Parliament; And for the continuance of an uſurped Chancery in <hi>Wales,</hi> the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency wherof briefly appears by the enſuing. <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96664:3"/>
            <head>A WARNING-PEECE FOR ENGLAND,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is ſayd of <hi>Tenures,</hi> That all Eſtates are held <hi>mediatly,</hi> or <hi>immediatly</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Supream Magiſtrate:</hi> So it may in as <hi>appoſite</hi> a Senſe be affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of <hi>Judicatory power,</hi> that all <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> is ſubordinate to the <hi>Supream Authority:</hi> There is and ought to be in one and the ſame <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or <hi>Empire;</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Scale of Judicatory continued in an orderly <hi>concatenation</hi> of <hi>Superiority</hi> and <hi>Inferiority,</hi> until there be at laſt a <hi>concentration</hi> of all in that ultimate Right of <hi>Soveraignty;</hi> He that ſhall contradict this <hi>Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> of <hi>Powers,</hi> ſeems in my judgment equally <hi>obnoxious</hi> unto <hi>cenſure,</hi> as thoſe that ſhall maintain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96664:4"/>that there ought to be no order or degree amongſt particular men, all power is either <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi> or <hi>delegated,</hi> and without peradventure the power <hi>delegate</hi> ought to be <hi>dependent</hi> upon that from which it is deduced: to pretend authority in the lower Spheares of <hi>delegated Juriſdiction,</hi> that ſhall be unreſponſall to the <hi>higher</hi> is <hi>little better</hi> then a criminall and contemptuous arrogance, which truly I can call no leſſe then a degree of Deniall to the <hi>Supremacy</hi> it ſelfe: that the <hi>Summa poteſtas</hi> ſhould be ſecured with this Life-gard Maxime of Policy, <hi>Immunity of puniſhment and unqueſtionablneſs for Error:</hi> I would readily allow as conceiving it rationall and agreeable to the rules of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for there muſt be a <hi>ſons Juſtitiae a Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier reſort</hi> upon whoſe determination all <hi>litigant</hi> and <hi>diſſenting</hi> parties muſt quietly ſit down and acquieſce. But to ſet up particular inferior Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, of what condition ſoever in ſuch <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount Stations</hi> as to be exempt from the benefit of <hi>appeals,</hi> as it is a <hi>ſolaeciſme</hi> in Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Preſident, ſo would it tend to nothing but to gratifie the <hi>ſupercillious minds</hi> of <hi>corrupt and ambitious men:</hi> and conſequently ſet up ſo many <hi>Exorbitant Dictators</hi> in the place of <hi>Judges</hi> who may exerciſe their <hi>Arbitrary wills and tyrannies,</hi> and grind the faces of the people, <hi>cum privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96664:4"/>
'Twere to be wiſhed that all ſuch as are reall freinds and relate to that <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> would addreſſe themſelves to thoſe that ſit in <hi>Judicature</hi> in the <hi>Welſh Counties</hi> and therby to repreſent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to their conſideration how fatall and peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a thing it is to any Court or Juriſdiction to ſeek to advance their own authority by <hi>incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon another power</hi> (eſpecially where that power is the <hi>Superior</hi>) Many freſh inſtances might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in theſe latter times of ſeverall Courts that have had their downfal from this <hi>Pinacle of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Let the <hi>Councell</hi> of the <hi>Marches</hi> for all the reſt be mentioned for one ſingle <hi>Memorial</hi> &amp; <hi>monument</hi> of the unhappineſſe of this <hi>Error:</hi> other Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples I omit, the truth hereof being notorious enough to the moſt careles obſerver. I am really perſwaded that 'tis not the unanimous opinion of all thoſe judges that ride the <hi>Welſh Circuits</hi> that thoſe Writs of <hi>Certiorar. Habeas Corpor.</hi> and <hi>Writs of Error &amp;c.</hi> ſhould not be allowed, But am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the moſt of them <hi>More Majoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their <hi>Subordination</hi> and <hi>dependance,</hi> which is an argument to me more cogent, then a <hi>Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that they that promote this project for aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Writs (for I can call it little better) are agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated &amp; by aſſed by ſome private intention to <hi>a gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize</hi> themſelves rather then upon pure and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96664:5"/>principles of <hi>conveniencie</hi> and <hi>zeale</hi> to the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like welfare,</hi> before ſuch attempts as theſe, tis known thoſe Courts of <hi>Wales</hi> continued in great ſplendor and reputation, under the power and management of <hi>wiſe moderate and Learned Judges and Officers,</hi> But if now they ſhall not containe themſelves within their antient <hi>Land-Markes,</hi> thoſe <hi>Earthen potts</hi> may, it is to be feared, be broken in peeces, by daſhing againſt thoſe that are of more ſolid <hi>Materialls,</hi> what the pretenders of this innovated priviledge (for exempting the inhabitants of <hi>Wales</hi> from appeale upon <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Error Habeas Corpor. Cerciorar. &amp;c.</hi> (being the antient rights of the people) can ſay for themſelves, is beyond my apprehenſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
            <p>To affirme that it is againſt Law would ſmell of groſſe or willfull Ignorance, or elſe which is worſe, affected Arrogance; For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is a ſufficient reaſon in <hi>Law</hi> that the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ever ſince the erecting the Juriſdiction in <hi>Wales</hi> hath warranted <hi>Certiorar.</hi> and in theſe times when thoſe parts were ſupplyed with as <hi>learned Judges</hi> as any the Nation afforded, and for writs of <hi>Error</hi> the Statute of <hi>Wales</hi> directs where they ſhal be brought <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> in <hi>perſonalls</hi> in the <hi>Marches;</hi> in <hi>mixt</hi> and <hi>real</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> as for Criminall cauſes.</p>
            <p>It is the opinion of the moſt <hi>learned Lawers</hi> of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96664:5"/>
               <hi>Nation</hi> that <hi>Certiorar.</hi> upon the Statute of 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. do lye in <hi>Wales</hi> for removall of all <hi>Inditements</hi> for <hi>Felonie, Murther Man-ſlaughter,</hi> and other <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> there committed to be tryed in the next adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Engliſh County.</hi> And that by the ſame Statute any of the <hi>Inhabitant</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> may be indited and tryed in the next adjadent <hi>Engliſh County</hi> for a Fact committed in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The practice wherof being frequent in caſes ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as well in <hi>North-wales</hi> as <hi>South-wales,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preſidents might be inſtanced and produced in that behalf: And the words of that <hi>Stature</hi> are very plain and pregnant to warrant the ſame; But in caſe the Statute had been dark or dubious, yet by <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Law</hi> an <hi>Appeal</hi> lyeth without expreſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion as out of <hi>Ireland, Galice, County Palatine. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By the Statute of the 27th. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were <hi>incorporated,</hi> and by the words of that Law, the <hi>Inbabitants of Wales ſhall have and enioy all Rights, Fran biſes, Liberties, Priviledges,</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> within England, <hi>as any of the Inhabitants there being born Subiects ſhould have, or enioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>England</hi> enjoy the benefit of <hi>Certiorar. Habeas Corpora, Writs</hi> of <hi>Error, Quo minus,</hi> and <hi>Subpaenas</hi> out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and <hi>Subpae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> out of <hi>Chancery</hi> (which Court ought to be alwaies open for the releife of all Suitors.)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96664:6"/>and conſequently the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſayd <hi>Statute</hi> ought to enjoy the like <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, Franchiſes, Liberties, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges;</hi> Since which time they have lived peaceably under the ſame Law &amp; Government, which the moſt ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and knowing amongſt them deſire ſtill to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; Who cannot but look on the promoters of this <hi>innovated Juriſdiction</hi> amongſt them as perſons that go to ſeperate <hi>Wales</hi> from <hi>Eng.</hi> to the <hi>indangering the peace therof,</hi> and to debarre all <hi>Wales</hi> of thoſe <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges Lawes and immunities</hi> which were gratiouſly made and eſtabliſhed for that benefit, and ſuch as do herein as they have done in other things elſe do deem themſelves to be <hi>enemies to their Native Country and the Peace and Tranquillity therof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Statute of the 34 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. which eſtabliſheth the <hi>Welſh Juriſdiction</hi> is an <hi>affirmative Stat.</hi> and was meerly granted in Favor of <hi>Wales</hi> by way of additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall <hi>Priviledge</hi> and <hi>Liberty;</hi> But doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thoſe <hi>Lawes, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> which were eſtabliſhed for their benefit by the ſayd prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Statute of 7 <hi>H.</hi> 8. nor doth abridge them from the benefit of any Priviledge or Liberty which they might claim before thoſe Statutes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Tis repugnant to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>common Juſtice,</hi> that an <hi>Inferiour Court</hi> ſhould be ſet up that is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>erre,</hi> and yet ſhould not be ſubject to an <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96664:6"/>
6. The <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> is derived from the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Iudges</hi> there fit by <hi>Patent</hi> made under the <hi>great Seal</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Tis agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reaſon that the <hi>Chancery</hi> that gives them their <hi>Power</hi> ſhould be capable to ſend a Writ of <hi>Error</hi> to them and force <hi>obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Certiorar.</hi> and <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> commeth out of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench,</hi> the Court of the <hi>Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi> where he himſelf is ſuppoſed to ſit, and hath <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> in <hi>Criminall Matters,</hi> and muſt be obeyed therin upon <hi>pain</hi> of <hi>contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. It is obſerved that ever ſince the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of <hi>VVales</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> by the Statute of 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Writs of <hi>Error,</hi> and <hi>Habeas Corpora,</hi> have never been deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor oppoſed by any untill within this two years, by one Mr. <hi>John Corbet</hi> Juſtice in <hi>Brecon, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gwyn <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gninſt</hi> Corber, Hill. 1654.</note> A Writ of <hi>Errror</hi> was oppoſed in the caſe of <hi>Kees Gwin</hi> Gent. But on full debate therof by learned Councel on both ſides before the preſent <hi>Lords Commisſioners of the great Seal of England:</hi> Their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> declared their Opinion that the Writ of <hi>Error</hi> did unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably lye and iſſue into <hi>VVales,</hi> and the <hi>Iudges</hi> there ought to yeild <hi>obedience</hi> therto; And the ſayd Court impoſed ſeverall <hi>Penalties</hi> on the ſaid Mr. <hi>Gorbet</hi> for his <hi>wilfull contemning</hi> the ſayd <hi>Writ</hi> and the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>High Court of Chancery,</hi> from whence he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Commiſſion.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96664:7"/>
9. As for the Writ of <hi>Quo ininus</hi> it is warrantable likewiſe by Law.<note place="margin">Keleway, 138 Quo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>out of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer and</hi> Capias us lagatum <hi>out of the common Pleas iſſue into</hi> Wales</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe in <hi>tranſitory Actions</hi> a man may ſue where he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Quo minus</hi> is a <hi>Prerogative VVrit</hi> found out for releif of the Kings Debtors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Principalitie of VVales</hi> is, and alwaies was held of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and therfore the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants therof properly ſuable before the <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> to which place they are Accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The liberty of ſuing in the <hi>Chequer</hi> by <hi>Quo minus,</hi> or <hi>Subpaenas</hi> hath been, <hi>time out of mind</hi> uſed and practiſed without <hi>contradiction</hi> and without queſtion if the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> did not find more <hi>benefit</hi> therby, and more <hi>indifferent</hi> juſt <hi>proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> there, then in their own <hi>Country;</hi> it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable they would travell ſo far for <hi>Iuſtice</hi> whilſt it is in the <hi>choice</hi> of the Plaintiff where he will bring his <hi>Action,</hi> and ſurely no Plaintiff will probably ſue in the <hi>Chequer</hi> without very good cauſe of Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Court provideth <hi>coſts</hi> for the Defendant ſuitable to the nature of his <hi>Expence,</hi> and where the Inhabitants of <hi>VVales</hi> ſhould be abridged or debarred of this <hi>ancient Freedom, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,</hi> no indifferent unbyaſſed perſon can afford a ſatisfactory reaſon. And the rather becauſe the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96664:7"/>matter comes to be tryed in the <hi>next adjacent Engliſh County,</hi> not farr from their own Habitation, nor yet ſo <hi>remote</hi> as the late <hi>Council at Marches</hi> was to moſt parts of <hi>Wales.</hi> And tryals of this nature give great ſatisfaction both to Plaintiffs and Defendants, when they have choice of <hi>learned men</hi> to plead their Cauſes before <hi>learned Judges,</hi> and <hi>able indifferent Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> of no <hi>relation</hi> to Plaintiffs or Defendants to try their Cauſes.</p>
            <p>But it is posſible that the <hi>legallity</hi> according to the preſent <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> may not be much contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, and therfore it muſt not ſuffice to reſt there. It ſhall be my next task to make known and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to thoſe that wil not wilfully hood-wink them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>undiſpenſable neceſsity</hi> of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing this <hi>ancient, laudable,</hi> and <hi>approved Conſtitution</hi> concerning the removall of Actions or Suits from or beginning them elſewhere, then in <hi>Wales,</hi> where the cauſe of Suit is firſt <hi>emergent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the firſt place give me leave to ſay, I hold this <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>Appeal</hi> as great a <hi>priviledge</hi> as any is compriſed within the <hi>great Charter of our Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> There are many living whoſe experience will teſtifie to this Truth, had not their ſufferings made them incapable to be produced as Witneſſes, and others of <hi>foreſeeing judgments</hi> and <hi>perſpicacity</hi> that will readily maintain that this <hi>aſſertion</hi> is no <hi>Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96664:8"/>For my part I make no difference in relation to every <hi>Engliſh mans general Birth-right</hi> by the Law, between a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and theſe other Writs of <hi>Error Certiorar, Quo minus, &amp; Subpaena</hi> out of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer</hi> and <hi>Subpaena</hi> out of the <hi>High Court of Chancery;</hi> And how grievous the complaints of the people have been in all times, when Writs of <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora</hi> be obtained; Preſidents of former times ſpeak loudly of, and the noiſe therof hath wrung in all mens eares: But to make the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Poſition</hi> the more delucidly appear, it will be convenient to deſcend to ſome particular <hi>numericall</hi> reaſons for the maintenance of it, which may be thus Marſhalled.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All County <hi>Iuriſdictions</hi> muſt of neceſſity be more <hi>obnoxious</hi> to <hi>partialities</hi> in their proceedings, then thoſe that are of more <hi>univerſall latitude,</hi> they are ſo circumſcribed within ſo ſmall a Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that the <hi>Iudge</hi> although never ſo upright and vigilant will be more eaſily abuſed, the <hi>Iurors</hi> more lyable to be <hi>packed</hi> or <hi>miſled,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> in all Cauſes more readily <hi>wrought upon</hi> and <hi>corrupted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This reaſon (as may be ſuppoſed) was not the leaſt motive to the late <hi>Parliament</hi> that gave the break-neck to the Deſigne ſet on foot for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincialls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that it is more then apparant the preſent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96664:8"/>to make the Welſh <hi>Iuriſdiction abſolute</hi> and <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent,</hi> tends not only to the deprivement of <hi>Wales,</hi> of their <hi>ancient Rights, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Freedoms</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law, but if granted, would prove a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident</hi> of <hi>dangerous conſequence</hi> to all the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as herein afterwards is more fully declared.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is very well known to thoſe that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the nature and condition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Wales,</hi> that before the late <hi>Wars,</hi> &amp; at this time there were, and are ſuch <hi>Family Emulations</hi> and <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> for the moſt part in the ſeverall Counties, that the whole body of them is apt to be caſt upon every ſlight controverſie into <hi>Factions Confederacies</hi> and <hi>parties,</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>infection</hi> therof doth not only remain amongſt the <hi>Vulgar</hi> and <hi>private</hi> men, but often times doth attach the very <hi>Bench</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and by that means tis not imposſible but it may ſomtime catch hold of the <hi>Iudge</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is obſerved that ſince the late <hi>VVars,</hi> theſe <hi>Differences</hi> have been ſo increaſed, and the ſpirits of men ſo highly provoked, that of late years (as I am informed) the <hi>civill, Military,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Powers</hi> there have been uſed and converted by ſome, more for private <hi>vindication</hi> and <hi>revenge</hi> on their Neighbours and Country-men, then for the reall diſcharge of <hi>publike truſt;</hi> Inſomuch that the <hi>cries</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> have been very loud though <hi>helpleſs,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96664:9"/>and ſhould the <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lales</hi> be made <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi> and <hi>independent</hi> without <hi>Appeals,</hi> then without queſtion all (except ſuch as are intruſted with the <hi>Authority</hi>) and their Friends and Relations muſt needs be unſafe <hi>in their lives, liberties, and Eſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Thoſe that are converſant with the Welſh Proceedings, do obſerve, that if the matter concern any perſon of <hi>awe</hi> or <hi>eminence,</hi> there is moſt commonly ſuch <hi>relation</hi> between the <hi>Parties, Iury,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itneſſes</hi> either in reſpect of <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, tenure</hi> or other <hi>dependa ce,</hi> that ſome out of wretched ſimplicity, others our of wilfull perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will make but a <hi>Cypher</hi> of the man upon the Bench, and think they diſcharge not their duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they find for their <hi>Kinſman,</hi> their <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. But ſuppoſe that the caſe of controverſie fall out between a <hi>Native</hi> and an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience hath taught ſome that <hi>mediet as linguae</hi> is in no caſe more neceſſary then here; For the firſt Inquiry or whether he be <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gle Cheria</hi> or no, and I may then ſay without traducing of that Country, that the ſame Injury or Fact committed upon a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> will many times not be found ſo when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon an Engliſh-man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If it be objected, that <hi>Appeals</hi> to the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by <hi>Habeas Corpora, Certiorar. Writs of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96664:9"/>Error, &amp;c.</hi> occaſion <hi>delay,</hi> and <hi>expence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It cannot be denyed by any, but that <hi>delatory Juſtice</hi> is more deſirable then perverted, and the <hi>Appellant</hi> bears the greateſt <hi>burthen,</hi> who probably will not <hi>appeal</hi> without good cauſe to warrant his proceedings therin, for beſides his own <hi>charges</hi> he muſt pay conſiderable <hi>coſts</hi> (if in <hi>civill Cauſes</hi>) to the other party if he make not good his <hi>Appeal,</hi> if in <hi>criminall Caſes,</hi> the charge of bringing it to the teſt, beſides the re-inforcing of the <hi>Judgment</hi> given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if he fail to make good his <hi>Appeal,</hi> is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>check</hi> to all <hi>Cauſeleſſe Appellants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If it be objected, that Tryals upon <hi>Quo minus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Subpaenas out of the Exchecquer</hi> are <hi>chargeable</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory,</hi> becauſe they are tranſmitted for tryall into <hi>forraign Counties,</hi> and that the <hi>remoteneſs</hi> of the place is a <hi>diſcouragement</hi> to parties and their Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1. That Objection will prove of little force if the <hi>conveniency</hi> of having the ſame tryed before <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> and <hi>impartiall Judges</hi> and <hi>Jurors</hi> in the next adjacent <hi>County</hi> be duly conſidered, where Cauſes are determined with <hi>equal</hi> and <hi>quicker diſpatches,</hi> then the ordinary courſe of Juſtice in the great <hi>Sesſions</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> doth bear it, where many by reaſon of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentall <hi>delayes</hi> of late uſed there, are much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96664:10"/>to proſecute their Cauſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the extraordinary <hi>charges</hi> of <hi>Appeals</hi> from <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>erroneous Verdicts,</hi> and <hi>Judgments,</hi> be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into conſideration, occaſioned by the <hi>partiality</hi> and <hi>corruption</hi> of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Jurors,</hi> and others that have the <hi>tranſacting</hi> of the <hi>peoples cauſes,</hi> as hath been before demonſtrated; with this alſo, that in caſe a <hi>Welſh Sheriff</hi> be of the contrary <hi>faction,</hi> or a freind to the Plaintiff or Defendant; ſuch <hi>Iurors</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, againſt whom no <hi>exceptions</hi> can be made by <hi>Law,</hi> yet ſhall bring in a <hi>verdict</hi> rather according to the pleaſure of the <hi>Sheriff</hi> and the parttie he <hi>adheres</hi> unto, then according to the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>merits</hi> of the cauſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If it be conſidered where the trial by <hi>Law</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, although not in <hi>vicineta,</hi> yet in <hi>vicino Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatu</hi> in the neighbour County, although not in the neighbourhood, and it is often ſeen on trialls in the <hi>Welſh Counties,</hi> the parties are forced ſomtimes to bring <hi>witneſſes</hi> out of <hi>England</hi> 100. or 200. miles, or more, and ſomtimes out of the remoteſt partes of <hi>Wales</hi> even to this County of <hi>Mountgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The contrivers and promoters of <hi>Cantoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Wales</hi> to ſerve their own ambitious ends, do not only go about to deprive the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96664:10"/>of <hi>Wales</hi> of the benefit of <hi>Certiorar. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpora, Writs of Error, Quo minus, Subpaenas,</hi> out of the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> But would alſo make themſelves <hi>Lord Chancellors,</hi> as well as <hi>Lords cheif Iuſtices of Wales,</hi> and that no <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale</hi> might be hereafter made by any of the Inhabitants of <hi>Wales</hi> to the High Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> for the <hi>reveiw</hi> or <hi>reverſal</hi> of any <hi>decree,</hi> or other proceeding in the pretended court of <hi>Chancery</hi> there held, nor any addreſs to the ſaid High Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> by any of the <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> for releif upon <hi>Originall bills</hi> there filed, touching any matters <hi>reall, perſonal,</hi> or <hi>mixt,</hi> relating to <hi>Wales; all which</hi> ſufficiently teſtifieth the <hi>pride, ambition,</hi> and <hi>exorbitant thoughts</hi> and <hi>purpoſes</hi> of theſe <hi>Innovators,</hi> to make themſelves ſole and <hi>arbitrary Iudges,</hi> both of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> in all cauſes <hi>criminall</hi> and <hi>civill,</hi> to the indangering of the <hi>lives, liberties,</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> of all ſuch as are not, or ſhal not be intruſted with this <hi>Paramount authority,</hi> or are not or ſhall not be of relation to them.</p>
            <p>Wheras in truth if their <hi>Chancery Iuriſdiction</hi> be but inquired into, they have not the leaſt colour, much leſſe Commiſſion or authority to hold ſuch a <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> as they now do, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96664:11"/>for ſome late yeares have uſurped as I humbly conceive for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Iudges</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> have not any power either by the <hi>Stat. of Wales</hi> or their <hi>Commisſions</hi> to hold a court of <hi>chancery,</hi> nor yet by any anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>cuſtom</hi> or <hi>Preſcription;</hi> but its beginning was from the <hi>Councell</hi> of the <hi>Marches</hi> now aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on meer references transferred unto them, wherby color therof firſt retained <hi>petitions</hi> and afterwards <hi>bils</hi> in equity, neither can they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce eſpecially in <hi>South-wales</hi> one bil in equity preferred in this pretended Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> in <hi>Wales</hi> of 50. years ſtanding, there being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny living that well remember the time when no ſuch bills were retained but only equitable rules made at common law, either by the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſent or upon ſubmiſſion of the parties</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are no <hi>Officers</hi> ſetled nor <hi>ſworn,</hi> nor any ſet <hi>Fees eſtabliſhed</hi> in this <hi>welſh Chancery</hi> by any <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>legall</hi> authoritie, other then what the <hi>Judges</hi> there for ſome late yeares <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarily</hi> have <hi>erected,</hi> wheras the <hi>Fees</hi> and <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> in reference to their <hi>Gommon-Law Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> are certaine and prefixed by the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Welſh <hi>Chancery</hi> is a <hi>paper Court</hi> where
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96664:11"/>there are no <hi>records</hi> or inrolments kept of their proceedings, but their paper <hi>Records</hi> as they cal them, are commonly carried by <hi>Client,</hi> Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor, and <hi>Attorney,</hi> from place to place in their pockets, and often left and ſome times made uſe of to light Tobacco.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is queſtionable whether any perſon can be queſtioned or <hi>Indicted</hi> for <hi>perjury</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this <hi>Court,</hi> wherby the ſame may become a <hi>Nurſery</hi> for <hi>Perjury,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is a reaſon given by ſome that know the Country, why <hi>Perjury</hi> is ſo frequent in ſome of thoſe partes</p>
            <p n="5">5. To a Court of <hi>equitie</hi> a diſtinct <hi>Seale</hi> ought to appertain, to ſeale all their <hi>writs</hi> and inforce <hi>obedience</hi> to their proceedings: But to this pretended <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>equity</hi> no ſuch <hi>Seal</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth, yet aſſume they power to ſeal their <hi>Chancery writs</hi> with the <hi>Judiciall Seal,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to affix green wax, which is ſolely ordained by the Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. to Seale <hi>Judicial writs</hi> and not <hi>Chancery writs,</hi> and therfore as well may the <hi>Iudges</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench</hi> or <hi>Common Pleas</hi> or the <hi>Officers</hi> intruſted with the <hi>Seales</hi> therof affix green wax to the Writs Iſſuable out of the Higheſt Court of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96664:12"/>
               <hi>Chancery,</hi> and ſeal the ſame with their proper <hi>ſeal,</hi> and take the <hi>Fees</hi> due for the ſame, as the ſaid <hi>Iuſtices</hi> or their <hi>Clarks</hi> may ſeale the <hi>Writs</hi> or <hi>mandats</hi> which they Iſſue out of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Chancery,</hi> with their <hi>Common-law Seale</hi> by which they cannot inforce <hi>obedience</hi> to their pretended <hi>Chancery Iuriſdiction,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Orders and Decrees are of no force, but the people expoſed to fruitleſs trouble and expences, and that which can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to no reaſonable end, the Law rejects as a thing <hi>inutile</hi> and <hi>uſeleſſe, Sapiens incipit a fine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The High Court of <hi>Chancery</hi> time out of mind and memory of man, nay ever ſince the eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> on Bills exhibited there, have and do retain the ſame and give <hi>reliefe</hi> therein, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any <hi>Decree, Order</hi> or <hi>Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> in the pretended <hi>Chancery</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> againſt whoſe proceedings the ſaid Court have, and do grant <hi>Injunctions</hi> untill the hearing of the cauſe which were never diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed nor contradicted; nor ſuch proceedings found inconvenient untill within this 12. months, a Judge then and now in <hi>Wales</hi> drew
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96664:12"/>a Plea of a <hi>decree</hi> made before himſelf, in Bar of a bill exhibited in the High Court of <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> for releif of the ſame matter,<note place="margin">Owen <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, 1654.</note> but got an other Counſel to ſigne it, which being argued before the <hi>Lords Commiſ.</hi> and endeavored to be maintained by two <hi>Welſh Counſellors,</hi> that take upon them to be the principall upholders of this <hi>uſurped juriſdiction</hi> yet their <hi>Lord<hi rend="sup">ps</hi>. overru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and <hi>ordered the Defendants to anſwer in cheif,</hi> and granted an <hi>Injunction</hi> for ſtay of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the <hi>Chancery</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters here complained of, untill hearing of the cauſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. There are <hi>Preſidents</hi> that may be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe produced of <hi>Prohibitions</hi> Iſſued out of the Courts of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pretended <hi>Chancery of Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. A Court of <hi>Equity</hi> cannot be erected by <hi>grant</hi> or <hi>preſcription,</hi> but only by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hobart 5.87 Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>and</hi> Marſhall, Dyer 175 1 pr. Sproggs <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </note> and yet the <hi>Chancery</hi> in <hi>VVales</hi> hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>grant</hi> nor <hi>preſcription</hi> nor <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> for its ſupport, wherof the <hi>Judges</hi> of <hi>VVales</hi> being deeply ſenſible, and of the danger of incurring the penalties impoſed by the ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Statutes</hi> for <hi>Premunire</hi> in caſes of like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, have not untill now of late take upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96664:13"/>them the authority to make any <hi>finall</hi> or <hi>decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Orders,</hi> without the orders themſelves were firſt ſigned by the Counſel &amp; Attorneys on both ſides wherby the ſame were indeed made rather <hi>orders by conſent</hi> of both parties their <hi>Counſell</hi> and <hi>Attorneys,</hi> then any <hi>finall</hi> or <hi>decretal</hi> orders by a <hi>Chancery Iuriſdiction</hi> which indeed gives them no more <hi>authority</hi> then if the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were referred by conſent of all parties by way of <hi>Arbitration</hi> to ordinary <hi>Arbitrators,</hi> and how farr any have acted beyond their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſion or contrary to the Statutes for <hi>Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire;</hi> is humbly ſubmitted to conſideration, there being no Regiſter there untill of late.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To give the <hi>Iudges</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> the power of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> in all caſes <hi>criminall</hi> and <hi>civill,</hi> without <hi>Appeals</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> that the wiſdome of former ages never yet thought ſafe to intruſt to any perſons of never ſo much integrities &amp; abilities, nor any could be found ſo immodeſt as to accept much leſſe to deſire it, until few of late, and it is well hoped that the <hi>ſupream Authority</hi> wil take ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al notice of the contrivers &amp; promoters of this <hi>deſign</hi> being a few out of <hi>Brecknock Shire,</hi> where <hi>Iohn Corbet <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> doth ride as <hi>ſole Iuſtice;</hi> is upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96664:13"/>occaſion of a murder ther lately commited by ſome that are of neer relation to thoſe that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on this deſign, with an intention to ſmother this murther, and ſave the lifes of few from the power of Juſtice, with the vtter ruine of the whole Country, as is herein after more fully diſcovered.</p>
            <p>The granting ſuch a power of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> in one or more perſons, is to ſet up <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarines,</hi> and to deſtroy the <hi>fundamental Lawes</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> as <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the <hi>Petition of right,</hi> and <hi>tryals</hi> by 12. <hi>men &amp;c. For</hi> after a <hi>verdict</hi> at <hi>Law</hi> the ſame perſon that ſits as <hi>Judge</hi> therof, may if he pleaſe, as <hi>Chancellor</hi> ſtop <hi>Indgment,</hi> or after <hi>Iudgment</hi> ſtay <hi>Execution,</hi> or if he pleaſe <hi>ſtop the tryall</hi> it ſelf, and in one mans caſe <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter</hi> the <hi>ſtrictnes of Law,</hi> but in another mans caſe of the ſame nature, <hi>Adminiſter</hi> his own <hi>will</hi> for <hi>rules of equitie:</hi> And ſo carry <hi>fire</hi> in one hand, and <hi>water</hi> in another hand, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a power that many <hi>learned</hi> honeſt <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious</hi> men would not accept off, if offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as <hi>Inconſiſtent</hi> w<hi rend="sup">h</hi> the rules of <hi>good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> in the due <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of <hi>juſtice;</hi> &amp; if once this power was erected in <hi>Wales;</hi> then by the ſame rule of <hi>Law</hi> &amp; reaſon may ſome <hi>ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96664:14"/>perſons</hi> petition for eſtabliſhing the like <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> in all other parts of this <hi>Nation</hi> that are but 30. or 40. miles diſtant from <hi>London,</hi> &amp; therby reduced the whole <hi>Nation</hi> into ſeverall <hi>Provinces</hi> under an <hi>Arbitrary mixt power</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>equity</hi> in one and the ſelf ſame perſons, to the ſubverſion &amp; overthrow of the <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal rights, laws, liberties,</hi> and <hi>freedoms</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Far be it from any ſober man as much as to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that the Wiſdome and Juſtice of his <hi>Highnes</hi> the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> and his Counſel wil ever condiſcend to ſuch unſafe deſtructive At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, the effecting wherof would not only draw a <hi>ruine inſenſibly</hi> upon the whole <hi>Nation;</hi> But endanger the very <hi>Root</hi> of <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas, now the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate</hi> hath the mediate overſeeing of all the <hi>Judges</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> and they have an <hi>inſpection</hi> into the proceedings of all <hi>delegated</hi> and <hi>ſubordinate Judges</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> and a power to releive the <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>oppreſſed</hi> and puniſh the <hi>guilty;</hi> wherby the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate</hi> may overſee the proceedings of all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> in and through the <hi>Chryſtal Fountain</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> alwayes ought to flow from the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for the relei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and refreſhing of all the <hi>oppreſsed injured</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96664:14"/>people of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and therby the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate</hi> is the better enabled as <hi>Iudge</hi> over all <hi>Iudges</hi> to <hi>diſcern</hi> and <hi>determine</hi> ſuch <hi>differences</hi> as ſhall or may ariſe either between the <hi>people</hi> or the ſeverall <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Adminiſter equal right</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> to all the people under his Highneſs <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaſt this diſcourſe might fall into the hands of ſome incredulous perſons that are no wayes concerned to take notice of the manner of the proceedings in <hi>Wales;</hi> give me leave to preſent to your conſideration, three <hi>Affidavit,</hi> the Original wherof remain of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the Chancery, and upper Bench; which will in great meaſure fortifie the veritie of the foregoing concluſions, and I dare affirm, if all other paſſages of like nature that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the great Seſſions held in thoſe parts, this little treatiſe would ſwel into too great a Volume.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavits">
               <body>
                  <div type="affidavit">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thomas Watkins</hi> of <hi>Bulith</hi> in the County of <hi>Brecon.</hi> Gent. maketh Oath that <hi>Elizabeth Williams</hi> mother of <hi>Roger Price</hi> late deceaſed finding one <hi>Jeffery Williams</hi> at the laſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany Quarter Seſſions held in <hi>Brecon</hi> did in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96664:15"/>Court lay hands on him and charged him with the murther of the ſaid <hi>Roger Price</hi> her ſon, and acquainted the Juſtices, of the peace then and there ſitting, that the ſaid <hi>Roger Price</hi> was dead of the ſtab, and wounds received of the ſaid <hi>Jeffery Williams, Hugh Williams</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>David Williams,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Thomas,</hi> and prayed the Juſtices to commit the ſaid <hi>Jeffery williams</hi> then &amp; ther preſent to the Goal, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might be proceeded againſt according to law; Nevertheles the ſaid <hi>Jeff. Williams</hi> was left at liberty upon ordinary Bayl to appear at the laſt great Seſsions for the County of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Ieffery Williams</hi> hath ſince been permitted to ride armed with his ſword, and the ſaid <hi>David Williams</hi> with a fouling peece to the great terror of the mother, wife and freinds of the ſaid <hi>Roger Price,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>David Williams</hi> having threatned <hi>Thomas Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> brother to the ſaid <hi>Roger</hi> for appearing for the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> againſt him, and the reſt of the offenders in order to the bringing them to a faire tryall; And the ſaid <hi>David Williams</hi> did ſhoulder and joſtle <hi>Elizabeth VVilliams</hi> the mother whilſt ſhe was going peaceably in the ſtreet, that the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Williams</hi> taking
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96664:15"/>notice of the premiſes and of the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance given the malefactors, finding their power and intereſt to be too potent for the Proſecutor in the ſaid County of <hi>Brecon.</hi> where ſhe could not hope for a faire and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different tryall and proceedings againſt them, did imploy this Deponent being uncle to the ſaid <hi>Roger price</hi> to ſue out a <hi>Certiorar.</hi> out of this Court for removing the Coroners Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to this Court in order to a fair tryall, in an indifferent Engliſh County, who on ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty given to proſecute with effect, obtained the ſame, &amp; delivered the ſaid writ to the Coroner, ſince the Inquiſition made, by which the ſaid parties were found guilty of Man-ſlaughter on the Statute of ſtabbing, of the firſt of <hi>King Iames:</hi> ſince which time at the laſt great Seſsions held at <hi>Brecon.</hi> before <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Juſtice there, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> was moved in open Court that the ſaid <hi>Ieffery Williams</hi> then and there preſent in Court might ſtand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted according to Law, and acquainted Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> that the Inquiſition was found, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> ſeeming highly diſpleaſed with the removal therof, did check and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance the proſecutors Counſel and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted other Counſel to ſpeak againſt the ſaid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96664:16"/>writ and removall of the Inquiſition, and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Iones</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Attorny Generall there for the Lord Protector not ſpeaking one word in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Lord Protector, and the Proſecutors in that behalf; but on the contrary moved that the ſaid <hi>Ieff. Williams</hi> might ſtand on his bayl; And further depoſeth that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Corbet</hi> committed the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Williams</hi> mother of the ſaid <hi>Roger Price,</hi> and one of the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and ſuffered the ſaid <hi>Jeff. Williams</hi> to go at liberty on his bayl, and did not aſmuch as Iſſue a Warrant to apprehend any of the ſaid Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but did alſo ſo far appear againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors and the Intereſt of the Lord Protector that he checked the Coroner and called him a knave and examined him againſt himſelf on oath in court meerly for his careful diſcharge of his duty on the Lord Protectors behalf: as this Deponent verily believeth; &amp; the ſaid M. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet</hi> did examin the foreman of the Jury in open Court againſt the Coroner &amp; the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Intereſt, &amp; againſt himſelf as this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent taketh it, and afterwards privatly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him in his Chamber, and refuſed to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter an oath to the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Williams</hi> on her <hi>Affidavit</hi> produced in writing touching
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96664:16"/>the Premiſſes, a true Coppy wherof is hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to annexed although the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her ſelf to be ſworn to the truth therof, firſt in his Chamber, and afterwards in open Court who then kept the ſame: Wherfore, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the potency of the Malefactors in the ſaid County this deponent being Uncle to the ſaid <hi>Roger Price</hi> deceaſed, and one of the Proſecutors for the Lord Protector cannot hope, or expect to obtaine Juſtice, or any fair or indifferent proceedings in the ſaid County of <hi>Brecon.</hi> againſt the ſaid Malefactors, for the ſaid horrid murther wherof they ſtand as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid indicted; And the rather in regard <hi>John Williams</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> late high Sheriff of the ſaid County being brother to 2. of the ſaid Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; and <hi>Edm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Attorny Gen. there, being a ſpecial friend to the ſaid <hi>Jo Williams</hi> &amp; his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who contrary to his duty the laſt great Seſſions neglected the Proſecution of the ſaid Malefactors; And further depoſeth that he was credibly informed that the ſaid Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and their Complices did way lay this deponent to take away his life, in his Journey to <hi>London</hi> this term.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Thomas Watkins.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Sworn</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>the 15th. day of</hi> May, 1655.</date> 
                           <hi>before me</hi> Hen: Roll.</dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="affidavit">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96664:17"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>REes Gwyn</hi> of <hi>Llanlloelvell</hi> in the county of <hi>Brecon.</hi> Gent. maketh oath that this depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent being indicted for Barretry in the County of <hi>Brecon.</hi> upon the malicious Proſecution of ſome of his adverſaries, and finding his Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors too potent in that County, where he could not expect to receive an indifferent and faire tryal, this Deponent did ſue forth a <hi>Certio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar.</hi> out of this Court of Vpper-Bench return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Michalemas</hi> Term 1653. in order to a fair tryal in an indifferent County, and delivered the ſame with the Fee to <hi>John Corbet</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> then, and yet Juſtice there; who allowed the ſame; &amp; this deponent paid the Prothonotaries Fees for certifiing the Record, that this deponent being before taken on proces to appear that Seſsions; and having given bond to the Sheriff for that purpoſe, and appeared, and had his writ of <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorar.</hi> as aforeſaid, allowed; The ſaid <hi>Iohn Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet</hi> did afterwards threaten to extreat the ſaid Bond, unleſs this Deponent would wave his <hi>Certiorar.</hi> which he was forc'd to do to ſave the ſuing of his ſaid Bond, which nevertheleſs was ſued: And this Deponent coming to try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all on his Traverſe, and twenty four able men returned by the Sheriff, the ſaid <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> did
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96664:17"/>lay aſide the ſaid Jury, and cauſed another Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be immediatly Impanelled, who were many of them, this Deponents profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and one of them; <hi>Viz. William Vaughan,</hi> one of the grand Jury-men who had firſt-found the Bill, by which means this Deponent was found guilty, and fined by the ſaid <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> 200 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> and ordered to be Impriſoned untill he ſhould pay it. And after ſome time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint this Deponent was diſcharged out of Priſon, with a purpoſe, as this Deponent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, to levy the Fine on his Eſtate, which in part was effected, and about the value of 40 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> of his Goods ſeiſed, and ſold for about 16 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> wherby he endured a double puniſhment for one ſuppoſed Crime, and this Deponent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſince by advice of Counſell taken out a Writ of Error in this cauſe, returnable in <hi>Hilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Term</hi> laſt, did deliver the ſame to the ſaid <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> at his own then dwelling place, and tendred him his Fee which he refuſed to allow; And in <hi>Hillary Term</hi> laſt, this Deponent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed the ſaid Writ returnable in <hi>Eaſter Term</hi> laſt, and again tendred him the Writ and his Fee at his then dwelling place, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed then to allow: But wiſhed this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96664:18"/>to tender it in Court at <hi>Brecon.</hi> Seſsions then next following, and there he would allow it. In purſuance wherof this Deponent did in <hi>Brecon.</hi> Seſsions held in <hi>April</hi> laſt, as well in his Chamber as in open Court, tender him the ſaid Writ &amp; his fee, which he refuſed to allow.</p>
                     <p>And this Deponent further depoſeth, that on his ſaid enlargment he was forced to be bound with two able Sureties in a Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of 400 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> for his appearance the firſt day of the laſt great Seſsions in <hi>Brecon.</hi> and in the mean time to be of the good behavior; Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Deponent, hath, as he doubts not but to make appear, performed the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Recognizance, and duly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and attended in Court every day of that Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and untill it was adjourned, yet ſince there is a <hi>Scirifacias</hi> ſued out on the ſaid Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance. By all which waies and means, this Deponent is in danger to be ruined in his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Credit, and Eſtate; The ſaid <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> having declared, he would addreſs himſelf to all the Judges of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and would uſe his utmoſt endeavour to have this Cauſe determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and concluded, by, and before himſelf and none other. And this Deponent is credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96664:18"/>and doubts not to make it appeare, that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Corbet</hi> ſo far appeared herein againſt this Deponent, that he ſollicited the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending of this Deponents Lands and Goods for the payment of the ſaid Fine, and applyed himſelf to ſeverall perſons for that purpoſe.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Rees Gwyn.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Sworn</hi> 
                           <date>7th: <hi>day of</hi> June, 1654.</date> 
                           <hi>before me</hi> Hen: Roll.</dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="affidavit">
                     <head>Between <hi>Rees Gwyn</hi> Gent. Plaintiff, <hi>John Corbet</hi> 
                        <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Defendant.</head>
                     <p>THe Plaintif <hi>Rees Gwyn</hi> maketh oath that ſince he this Deponent delivered the firſt writ of Error unto the Defendant, <hi>Corbet</hi> (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term 1653.) he this depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hath expended in Journyes to London, and otherwiſe, to force the Defendant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Writ of Error and Record into this Court of Vpper-Bench, above one hundred pounds, and upon the delivery of the laſt Writ of Error to the Defendant he demanded his Fee for allowing the writ in a jeering manner, uſing theſe words in open Court <hi>No penny no Pater Noſter;</hi> And although his Marſhal in his preſence and by his approbation received ſix ſhillings eight pence as a Fee therin, he the ſaid <hi>John Corbet</hi> hath not yet returned the ſame,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96664:19"/>though he then promiſed to return it. All which rends to this deponents great damage and prejudice.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Rees Gwyn.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Sworn</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 22. <hi>day of</hi> Feb. 1654</date> Edwin Rich.</dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THeſe things being premiſed what man of reaſon can eſteem it <hi>convenient</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr</hi> that <hi>Nation</hi> of ſo high a <hi>Birth-right</hi> as the benefit of <hi>Appeals</hi> to the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by <hi>Certiorar. Habeas Gorpus; Writs</hi> of <hi>Error, Quo minus</hi> and <hi>Subpaenas</hi> out of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and <hi>Subpaenas</hi> out of the High Court of <hi>Chancery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, if this ancient <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> be taken away, the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> will be deprived of the moſt conſiderable branch of <hi>liberty</hi> that belongeth unto them, &amp; I am perſwaded, &amp; partly know, that many of the moſt <hi>ingenious</hi> amongſt them, &amp; of <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtates</hi> there, wil be inforced to ſell their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances,</hi> &amp; forſake their own native <hi>Country:</hi> rather then live under ſuch an <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> as is herein before demonſtrated, which to a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or ingenious mind will be a greater bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage then to ſerve in the <hi>Callies</hi> as a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Slave.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
